<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here after foloweth a treatyse take[n] out of a boke whiche sometyme Theodosius the Emperour founde in Iherusalem in the pretorye of Pylate of Joseph of Armathy</title>
            <title>Here after foloweth a treatyse taken out of a boke whiche sometyme Theodosius the Emperour founde in Jherusalem in the pretorye of Pylate of Joseph of Armathy.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1511</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04678</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103814</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839559</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839559</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3990</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04678)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3990)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 69:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here after foloweth a treatyse take[n] out of a boke whiche sometyme Theodosius the Emperour founde in Iherusalem in the pretorye of Pylate of Joseph of Armathy</title>
                  <title>Here after foloweth a treatyse taken out of a boke whiche sometyme Theodosius the Emperour founde in Jherusalem in the pretorye of Pylate of Joseph of Armathy.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Flete strete at the sygne of the sonne by me Wynken de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Enprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1511?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Joseph, --  of Arimathea, Saint --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3990:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 64 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:3990:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 64 -->
            <head>Chere after foloweth a treatyſe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of a boke whiche ſomtyme Theodoſius the Emperour founde in Iheruſalem in the pretorye of Pylate of Ioſeph of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathy.</head>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>Iheſus nazarenꝰ rex iudeorum.</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:3990:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>Iheſus nazarenꝰ rex iudeorum.</head>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3990:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or aſmoche as oftentymes grete doub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes &amp; doubtefull thynges deceyueth the reders / therfore all doubtes ſette a parte ye ſhall ſe dyuers thynges extracte of the veray true &amp; probate aſſercyons of hyſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryal men touchynge and concernynge thantyquytes of thonourable monaſtery of oure lady in Glaſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burye. After the tyme that our ſauyour Iheſu cryſte was put vnto deth by paſſyon of the croſſe &amp; all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were fully complete whiche were wryten and ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken of hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by holy prophecye. That holy man Ioſeph of Armathy came vnto Pylate and aſked of hym the body of our ſauyour Iheſu cryſte / whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body was graunted to hym he wrapped it in a fayre whyte clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the and interyd it in a tombe newely made where ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer man was buryed in / what tyme the Iewes had parfyte knowlege that this Ioſeph had ſo worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully brought the body of cryſt in erthe / they thought vtterly in theyr myndes and keſt ſo alſo the meanes how they myght ſet handes vpon hym / &amp; one named Nychodemus and many dyuers other y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the veray true louers and iuſt aduocates of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyour fledde and kepte them ſecrete / excepte onely the ſayd Ioſeph &amp; Nychodemꝰ whiche full boldly pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſented them ſelfe &amp; made reherſall vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe wordes / what ſholde moue you to be dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs for aſmoche as we haue buryed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Iheſu cryſt / knowe ye full well ſayd Ioſeph &amp; Ny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodemus to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue myſdone agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghtfull man / ye caſt ne thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke not in your myndes the grete benefytes he hathe done and ſhewed to you
<pb facs="tcp:3990:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 66 -->ye haue for his grete goodnes crucyfyed hym &amp; with a ſharpe ſpere wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded hym. The Iewes herynge tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe wordes ſet hande on Ioſeph and cloſed hym in an houſe where was no wyndowe / &amp; annas &amp; cayphas ſealed the dore vpon the locke and aſſygned and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted cretayne men to kepe hym and watche hym and his felowe Nychodemus was let goo at lyberte. They intreated Ioſeph ſoo vngoodly for as moche that he was the man that deſyred the body of Iheſu cryſt / and was the pryncypall mouer and begynner that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body was ſo worſhypfully interyd &amp; buryed-after this was done vpon theyr ſabbat daye they ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deryd them in a companye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chefe rulers of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and caſte theyr myndes togyder how &amp; by what maner of dethe they myght deſtroye Ioſeph &amp; whan they were all in fere Annas and Cayphas were com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded by theym to preſent Ioſeph for as moche as they had ſealed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dore where he was incloſed in &amp; whan theyr ſeales were broken &amp; the dore opened Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeph was gone. Than they ſent out ſpyes to ſeke hym &amp; fynably he was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in his owne cyte called Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathya / &amp; whan they had redy tydynges &amp; perfyte knowlege of it / bothe chefe rulers &amp; all the comynal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of the Iewes inioyed gretely &amp; thanked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verray god of Iſraell y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was knowen where Ioſeph was become whiche was thus incloſed vnder kepy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and cuſtodye. Thenne they gadred in a multytude and they the whiche were pryncypalles and heedes prepoſynge this queſtyon and ſayd what meanes my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghte we fynde that we myght craftely haue Ioſeph vnto vs and ſo for to ſpeke with hym. Thenne they
<pb facs="tcp:3990:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 66 -->concluded generally that an epyſtle ſholde be wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vnto hym / and this was the effecte of the lettre. Ioſeph peace be with the and with all thy company. Nowe we knowe full well that we haue full greuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offended god and the / therfore we praye the vouch ſaue too come vnto vs that we maye comen with the for we meruaylle gretely how thou was taken out of the place in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche thou was putte / we knowlege ourſelfe vnto the that we haue malygned ſore agayn the / wherfore almyghty god hathe delyuered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> that our wycked counſeyll and vnhappye mynde myght not hurte the / therfore worſhyppefull Ioſeph whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che arte well beloued amonge all people / peace be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the. Thenne this epyſtle made and wryten they cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſeuen perſones amonge theym all whiche were the beſt and mooſt ſynguler frendes that Ioſeph had &amp; ſayd vnto theym / whan ye go forth take your way in to Aramathia vnto Ioſeph &amp; grete hym well in our behalue and take vnto hym this our epyſtle / whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeuen perſones electe &amp; choſen had theyr full anſwer with theyr lettre delyuered anone they came to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of Aramathya where Ioſeph was and full louyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gely ſalued hym ſhewynge theyr comynge &amp; the cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe gyuy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vnto hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> epyſtle whiche receyued them full curteyſly / and whan he had ouerloked the lettre and knewe the effecte thenne he ſayd theſe wordes. Bleſſyd be my lorde god of Iſraell whiche hathe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered and ſaued me that my blode hath not be ſhed nor I deſtroyed bleſſyd be my lorde god the whiche hathe kepte me vnder his wynges. Thenne Ioſeph in token of loue &amp; peace kyſſed the .vii. perſones whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:3990:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 67 -->were ſente in meſſage vnto hym and full kyndely hadde them into his houſe. And vpon the nexte daye after he toke his aſſe and walkynge kepte them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany vnto Iheruſalem. And whan the Iewes herde of his comynge they wente agaynſt hym and in their metynge ſayd with one voyce peace be in thy comyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge fader Ioſeph / and he reſaluted theym vnder this maner and ſayd. Peace be with you and amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge you all and there they kyſſed hym all / thenne Nychode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus receyued hym into his houſe and made hym a grete dyner / vpon a daye whan the Iewes were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered togyder Annas and Cayphas ſayd vnto Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph / ſhewe thou now before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god of Iſraell &amp; open<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly declare vnto vs ſuche thynges as we ſhall examyn the of for as moche as it is not vnknowen that we were ſore greued for by cauſe thou letteſt bury the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Iheſu cryſte and therupon we encloſed the in a preuy houſe and the morowe we ſent to haue ſpoken with the and myght not fynde the / wherfore we mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaylled gretely and were ſore affrayed of it how this myghte be vnto this tyme that we ſe the nowe / ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whyles thou arte preſente certefye vs verely ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we this mater was brought that thou was thus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretely conueyed awaye. Ioſeph dyſdayned not to gyue theym anſwere but ſayd vnto theym boldely. What tyme ye cloſed me in that houſe on godefry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daye the morowe vpon whiche is the ſabbate daye in the mydnyghte whan I was beſy in my prayers to deſyre god to be my helpe and ſocour / ſodeynly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane tyme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe that I was in was taken vp by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foure angles. And I ſawe Iheſus bryghter thenne
<pb facs="tcp:3990:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 67 -->ony lyght that euer I ſawe afore and for grete fere I fell downe to the erthe / thenne he toke me by the han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de frome the grounde and wyped my face with a ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and kyſſed me and ſayd vnto me be not aferde Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph loke vpon me and knowe thou full well that I am he. Thenne loked I vp and called hym mayſter Helyas ſuppoſynge that he hadde ben Hely the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete / thenne he ſpake vnto me and ſayd I am not Hely but I am Iheſus whoſe boody thou leteſt be buryed / thenne for by cauſe I was ſomdele doubtfull of it I ſayd vnto hym yf thou be he ſhewe me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be wherin I layde the. Thenne he toke me by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and broughte me vnto the place where I interyd hym. Furthermore he ſhewed me the clothe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I wrapped his body and alſo the ſudarye that I bounde his hede withall. Thenne theſe thynges ſeen I knewe well that it was Iheſus and I honoured hym as my dutye was recytynge theſe wordes. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyd be he that is come in the name of god. Thenne he toke me by the hande and ſoo ledde me in myn houſe in the Cyte of Aramathya &amp; ſayd vnto me reſte thou here peacybly theſe fortye dayes go not forth frome thy houſe. And I ſhall goo vnto my dyſcyples that hath grete luſte for to ſeme. And this ſayd and done. Iheſus vanyſſhed awaye. Thenne after theſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye dayes were hole and fullye complete Ioſeph of Aramathya aboue reherced ſtedfaſtly fyxed his myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de in the feruente loue of the fayth / gaue hym ſelfe to the dyſcyplyne and doctryne of ſaynt Phylyp the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle of our bleſſyd lorde Iheſu Cryſte. And whan that he was ſuffycyently inſtructe in his lore and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge
<pb facs="tcp:3990:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 68 -->/ bothe he and his ſone Ioſephes receyued of ſaynt Phylyp the holy ſacrament of baptyſme / and after that Ioſeph was ſente vpon a meſſage frome ſaynt Iohan the appoſtle &amp; euangelyſt from epheſye vnto the gloryous moder of Iheſu cryſte oure lady and alſo after that was preſente with ſaynt Phylyp and other dyſcyples what tyme that / that gloryous vyrgyn was aſſumpte in to heuen. And as many thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges as euer he herde and ſawe of oure lorde Iheſu cryſte and of his bleſſyd moder oure lady ſaynt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry / he ſhewed theym and preched theym in dyuerſe re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyons and places and conuerted moche people vnto the cryſten fayth and baptyſed them. And at the laſt. xv. yere after the gloryous aſſumpcyon of our bleſſyd lady he toke his ſone Ioſephes with hym and wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to ſaynt Phylyp in to Fraunce and conſequently as it is wryten in a boke called Graall Ioſeph of Ara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mathia whiche buryed the body of oure lorde Iheſu cryſte after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was baptyſed of the holy man ſaynt Phylyp the appoſtle came in to grete Brytayn whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was promyſed to hym and his yſſue &amp; he brought with hym his wyfe and his ſone Ioſephes whome our ſauyoure before that tyme hadde made a byſſhop and conſecrate hym in a Cyte called Sara / &amp; there came with hym ſyxe houdred perſones of men and women and mo / &amp; the men made a ſolempne vowe for to lyue chaſtely frome theyr wyues vnto the tyme they hadde entered in to grete Brytayne and all the nombre brake this vowe excepte. xxxvii. whiche we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by our ſauyour to paſſe ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſe ſaylyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge vpon the ſhyrte of Ioſephes and ſoo came to londe
<pb facs="tcp:3990:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 68 -->vpon Eſter euen in the mornyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſydue of them for as moche as they were penytent and ſory for the tranſgreſſyon of theyr vowe at thynſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; prayer alſo of Ioſeph were brought ouer in a veſſell whiche kynge Salamon crafrely had made to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynue and dure vnto cryſtes tyme / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame daye that theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panye came vnto londe vpon Ioſephs ſhyrte they applyed vnto londe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame veſſell whiche god had prouyded for theym whiche were gyded by a duke of Medor named Natianiis whome Ioſeph baptyſed byfore in the cyte of Sara / and with theym came al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the kynge of the ſame cyte called Mordrams to whome almyghty god after that appered &amp; ſhewed to hym his ſyde handes &amp; feet peryſſhed with the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re and nayles / and whan the kynge Mordrams ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we that he was moued with compaſſyon and ſayd. O my lorde god what man was ſo bolde and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous thus to dele with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / our ſauyour anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to hym agayne and ſayd. The falſe kynge of Nor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thwales hath this wyſe done with me whiche hathe put my ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Ioſeph of Aramathya with his com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany in pryſon and full vnky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly denyeth them theyr lyuy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge for by cauſe they ſhewed &amp; preched my name in his realme / therfore ſayd almyghty god vnto mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>drams / gyrde the with thy ſwerde aboute thy myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell and goo with all haſt poſſyble vnto that partyes and take vengeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vpon the tyraunt &amp; delyuer my ſeruauntes oute of pryſon &amp; daunger / whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge a woke of his ſlepe he was full glade of that vyſyon ſhewed vnto hym and ſo ſet his realme &amp; his houſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in good waye &amp; toke a grete company with hym &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:3990:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 69 -->toke his Iourney and as god was his guyde he came vnto the place where the kynge of Northwales the tyraunt was and commaunded hym he ſholde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte and ſuffre the ſeruauntes of almyghty god to paſſe out of pryſon and to be at lyberte / the tyraunt wolde not in no wyſe condeſcende vnto kynge Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drams commaundement / but with grete indygna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon charged hym ſhortely without delaye to voyde out of his londe whan kynge Mordrams herde this langage he came fyerſly vpon hym with his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and with and duke Naciamis aboue ſayd &amp; with condygne and Iuſte vengeaunce ſlewe hym / thenne this done kynge Mordrams wente vnto the pryſon where that vnhappye kynge hadde Ioſeph and his company in holde / &amp; with grete Ioye brought them forth and ſhewed vnto them the vyſyon made vnto hym of god and theyr delyuerynge thenne all they in grete myrthe thanked god hertely. Thenne kynge Mordradms gaue the realme &amp; kynge dome of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwales with the appertenence vnto one called Cely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>domus ſone vnto duke Nacyanus and gaue hym al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to be his wyfe Labell the ky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges doughter of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye whiche Labell the ſayd Celydomus with helpe and ſocoure of his fader hadde before with grete dyf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyculte conuerted vnto Cryſtes ſayth whoſe doubte and meruaylous actes be wryten in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bokes named Grall aboue reherced.</p>
            <trailer type="colophon">¶ Thus endeth the lyfe of Ioſeph of Armathy En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryted at London in Flete ſtrete at the ſygne of the ſonne by me Wynkyn de Worde.</trailer>
            <trailer type="illustration">
               <pb facs="tcp:3990:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 69 -->
               <figure/>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3990:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 70 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Wynkyn de Worde</head>
                  <p>W <figure>
                        <figDesc>printer's device of Wynkyn de Worde</figDesc>
                     </figure> C</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3990:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 70 -->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
